<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Artica Website</title>
        <description>We aim to transform emerging technologies and art into impactful human experiences. Artica digs electronics, education, robots, digital fabrication, prototyping, and all things creative.</description>
        <link>http://artica.cc/</link>
            <item>
                <title>Lisbon Mini Maker Faire</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Artica is sponsoring Lisbon Mini Maker Faire!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the truth is, we will have plenty of goodies at the Faire, so we will be looking forward for September. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information visit site official of &lt;a href=&quot;http://makerfairelisbon.com/pt/&quot;&gt;Mini Maker Faire.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://makerfairelisbon.com/pt/&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-07-02-makerfaire-1.png&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The curators team is already defined, they are doing their best to select the greatest projects of all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://makerfairelisbon.com/pt/2014/06/12/curators.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-07-02-makerfaire-2.png&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2014 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <link>http://artica.cc//blog/2014/07/02/mini_makerfaire.html</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://artica.cc//blog/2014/07/02/mini_makerfaire.html</guid>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>TedXKids @ CentralTejo</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-05-28-tedxkids.JPG&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again we had the pleasure to participate on &lt;a href=&quot;http://tedxkidscentraltejo.com/&quot;&gt;TedXKids @ CentralTejo&lt;/a&gt; with our Farruscos and a brand new workshop edition. Thanks Marta Gonzaga for inviting us once again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/94_LiRNPNZg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
 
</description>
                <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2014 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <link>http://artica.cc//blog/2014/05/28/tedxkids.html</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://artica.cc//blog/2014/05/28/tedxkids.html</guid>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>Infante Robots</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thebitbangtheory.com/pt/&quot;&gt;Mário Saleiro&lt;/a&gt; and Bruna Carmo presented us and Cesário Verde School with their innovative Learning System. This cute robots are true ice breakers for kids when it cames to learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-05-27-infantes_robots.jpg&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the great information is available at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thebitbangtheory.com/2013/11/robos-infante-sistema-de-robotica-educativa/&quot;&gt;http://www.thebitbangtheory.com/2013/11/robos-infante-sistema-de-robotica-educativa/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/Fglg0kaMBi4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
 
</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2014 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <link>http://artica.cc//blog/2014/05/27/infantes_robots.html</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://artica.cc//blog/2014/05/27/infantes_robots.html</guid>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>Magabot @ CUF 2013</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;About a year ago, in June 2013, we participated in &lt;a href=&quot;http://conferenciassaudecuf.com/2013&quot;&gt;Conferências saúde&lt;b&gt;cuf&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with a poster which at the time we forgot to post about on our blog. The poster was regarding our tests involving robotic remote presence, which took place in Hospital Dona Estefânia. Envisioning to develop a platform that would offer hospitalised children a way to travel and engage with the world while staying at the hospital. The work was developed in partnership with Paulo Alvito of &lt;a href=&quot;http://idmind.pt/&quot;&gt;IDMind&lt;/a&gt;, Francisco Dias, André Moreira and Hospital Dona Estefânia. It uses &lt;a href=&quot;http://magabot.cc&quot;&gt;magabot&lt;/a&gt;, our lowcost laptop on wheels robot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the poster in Portuguese:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-05-16-magabot-cuf-2013.jpg&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2014 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <link>http://artica.cc//blog/2014/05/16/magabot-cuf-2013.html</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://artica.cc//blog/2014/05/16/magabot-cuf-2013.html</guid>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>Workshop Tondela</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Last wednesday we were invited by Prof. Luis Dias to take Farrusco and the Robotics initiation Workshop at &lt;a href=&quot;http://eptondela.net/site/&quot;&gt;Escola Profissional de Tondela&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
Check out the vídeo made by Prof. Ricardo Silva!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/0SKydHUmKFY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-05-15-tondela.JPG&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-05-15-tondela_2.JPG&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2014 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <link>http://artica.cc//blog/2014/05/15/tondela.html</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://artica.cc//blog/2014/05/15/tondela.html</guid>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>Workshop José Castro</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;During last month we had a series of workshops with &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/josefgfcastro/&quot;&gt;José Castro&lt;/a&gt; which we would now like to share with the rest of the world. The goal of the workshops was getting his model of robotic survival behavior working with our &lt;a href=&quot;http://magabot.cc&quot;&gt;Magabot&lt;/a&gt;. The resulting source-code is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/artica/MLM-Logic-Machine-Magabot&quot;&gt;available online&lt;/a&gt; and so are the presentation slides &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;pid=sites&amp;srcid=ZGVmYXVsdGRvbWFpbnxqb3NlZmdmY2FzdHJvfGd4OjJiNTFkZDBjOTVmN2Q1YTM&quot;&gt;which were repurposed from SDIA2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also recorded some videos, they are in Portuguese though, apologies to our non Portuguese speaking site visitors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-05-14-magabot_MLM.png&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a total of three sessions. The first was a powerpoint presentation explaining how his robotic learning model works in theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/oyfjAtc0_KA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second work session was more hands-on, trying to get his python code that implemented his model working with one of our very own Magabot robots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/dCedfG5GePM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last session was a wrap up and showcase session, explaining in detail the different source files of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/ogtGpvZY4Z4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2014 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <link>http://artica.cc//blog/2014/05/13/magabot-mlm.html</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://artica.cc//blog/2014/05/13/magabot-mlm.html</guid>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>Microsoft Pizza Night</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;We were present on this year&amp;#39;s edition of Microsoft Pizza Night that took place on Microsoft&amp;#39;s own headquarters in Lisbon. Our team presented a customized version of Artica&amp;#39;s color voting system and Pong game that made such a buzz weeks ago on &lt;a href=&quot;http://artica.cc/blog/2014/04/14/codebits.html&quot;&gt;Sapo&amp;#39;s Codebits 2014&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pong game is an adaptation of the well known game. We already used it on &lt;a href=&quot;http://artica.cc/blog/2014/04/14/codebits.html&quot;&gt;Sapo&amp;#39;s Codebits&lt;/a&gt; and on &lt;a href=&quot;http://artica.cc/blog/2013/09/26/audience-pong.html&quot;&gt;Projecto 80&lt;/a&gt; events, but this time we made some funny graphical changes. The game&amp;#39;s paddles were made into rolling pins and the ball itself were transformed into a pizza that started to spin and move faster as the game was played. Crazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-04-28-pizzanight_1.JPG&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-04-28-pizzanight_2.JPG&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The color voting system was also customized for the event. The actual votes count was displayed as a... you guessed it, a pizza. The base pizza got filled with tasty ingredients in correlation with the actual positive votes from the crowd, so if a project didn&amp;#39;t had any love from the crowd, a flavorless pizza started to appear instead.&lt;br&gt;
Of course, we also had a numeric voting count that was shown, programmers like numbers after all. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/1zbnnWZvyrw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank all the Microsoft&amp;#39;s team involved in this project for such a fun night.&lt;br&gt;
A special thanks goes out to Miguel Vicente for organizing such a cool event and for the surprise candy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-04-28-pizzanight_3.jpg&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2014 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <link>http://artica.cc//blog/2014/04/30/pizzanight.html</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://artica.cc//blog/2014/04/30/pizzanight.html</guid>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>Codebits Pong CV Tech Report</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-04-22-codebits.png&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the &lt;a href=&quot;http://artica.cc/blog/2014/04/14/codebits.html&quot;&gt;Sapo Codebits 2014&lt;/a&gt; event, our clients Sapo/PT asked us to develop a computer vision module to help count the votes and entertain the audience. The entire project is open source &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/artica/audience-pong&quot;&gt;at the bitbucket repo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had already developed a similar project for &lt;a href=&quot;http://artica.cc/projects/interactive/2013/09/26/audience-pong.html&quot;&gt;Projecto 80&lt;/a&gt; but we wanted to take this wonderful opportunity to &lt;a hef=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/artica/bonsai.artica&quot;&gt;test and develop some modules&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/horizongir/bonsai&quot;&gt;Bonsai framework&lt;/a&gt;, since it&amp;#39;s being developed by a close friend of Artica, Gonçalo Lopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We re-implemented the computer vision modules using Bonsai. Testing it for use with multiple cameras and the new OSC message module, and integrated with our integration of XSockets module for Bonsai (based on &lt;a href=&quot;http://xsockets.net/&quot;&gt;XSockets.NET&lt;/a&gt;). You can find our version at &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/artica/bonsai.artica&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also includes some computer vision modules of our own. Some optimised functionalities were needed, mainly to the divise, merge and serialise image frames on realtime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/8KTkqO_PKfY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Pong we used standard HTML5 canvas client running on a modern browser (tested on Firefox 28 and Chrome 34). We used XSockets (with a .js library) to send the binary image of the camera from Bonsai to the browser, and also send weights information for the left and right paddles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The insert coin screens were ripped from early Sapo Codebits video teasers created by &lt;a href=&quot;http://hipnose.com&quot;&gt;Hipnose&lt;/a&gt; for Sapo. The bots are obtained in realtime from a list of participants of this years event, using the Codebits API to obtain the bot image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game is collaborative, not competitive. Both sides of the screen are attempting to keep the ball/bot in play for the longest possible time. On each hit it diminishes size and velocity increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The voting only has a computer vision module, the visuals were entirely on the application side of Sapo. We used a node.js server to receive the weights values  from Bonsai by OSC and rebroadcast them as standard websockets message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were required to do this on last minute because our target machine was using node.js and could not open any incoming ports. This would not allow it to be target of OSC. And there is no node.js library capable of receiving the xsockets kind of websockets. We hadn&amp;#39;t previously realized that Xsockets seems to wrap the websockets protocol instead of following the standard. So we had to set up a node.js server of our own that would broadcast the localhost osc messages to the target machine via standard websockets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <link>http://artica.cc//blog/2014/04/22/codebits_pong_cv_tech_report.html</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://artica.cc//blog/2014/04/22/codebits_pong_cv_tech_report.html</guid>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>Artica @ Codebits 2014</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;We were present at yet another edition of Sapo Codebits, happening again on Sala Tejo of MEO Arena, from 10 to 12 April 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were present at the Hardware Den area with a stand showcasing our robots, research projects and 3d printers. We even gave a couple introduction to robotics workshops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-04-14-codebits_1.jpg&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-04-14-codebits_5.jpg&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also did a little project for the organization, to help entertain the audience (playing collaborative pong) during the opening ceremony and innovate the way they counted votes. We developed a computer vision module using Bonsai to monitor the audience who had some red and green cards they could wave around and interact with. The project was somehow similar to our &lt;a href=&quot;http://artica.cc/projects/interactive/2013/09/26/audience-pong.html&quot;&gt;previous work for Projecto 80&lt;/a&gt; but we actually recoded it from scratch using Bonsai and HTML5 technology (there will be a tech report post following soon).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://rd3.videos.sapo.pt/playhtml?file=http://rd3.videos.sapo.pt/NuRAWAms8dISgkdlJfny/mov/1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-04-14-codebits_3.jpg&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Codebits have plenty of talks on different topics, this year André and Filipe gave one of them, about our adventures setting up &lt;a href=&quot;http://artica.cc/projects/interactive/2013/07/15/ciav-tech-report.html&quot;&gt;CIAV&lt;/a&gt;, it went pretty well, the video should be coming online soon (we will update this post with a link once it&amp;#39;s online). We also were present on the Portuguese Makers roundtable that took place Friday afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall the event went pretty well, we had lot of fun and met some very cool people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-04-14-codebits_4.jpg&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-04-14-codebits.jpg&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a video of the projects voting system in action (we did the computer vision module for it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/KC0FbYL5YsE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2014 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <link>http://artica.cc//blog/2014/04/14/codebits.html</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://artica.cc//blog/2014/04/14/codebits.html</guid>
            </item>
            <item>
                <title>Mostra de ensino Secundário e Superior de Almada</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-04-01-mostra_de_ensino.jpg&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we were at the public showcase of Secondary Schools and Universities of Almada&amp;#39;s municipally showing our educational robots &lt;a href=&quot;http://artica.cc/projects/education/2014/03/18/farrusco.html&quot;&gt;Farrusco&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://artica.cc/projects/education/2013/12/02/magabot.html&quot;&gt;Magabot&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://artica.cc/projects/customrobotics/2011/12/30/sapobot.html&quot;&gt;Sapobot&lt;/a&gt; was also there showing its abilities and skills in autonomous navigation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;postimage&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/2014-04-01-mostra_de_ensino_01.jpg&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://campodeflores.com/&quot;&gt;Colégio Campo de Flores&lt;/a&gt; for the opportunity!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2014 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <link>http://artica.cc//blog/2014/04/01/mostra_ensino_almada+copy.html</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://artica.cc//blog/2014/04/01/mostra_ensino_almada+copy.html</guid>
            </item>
    </channel>
</rss>